<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Quotes | Mike English&#x27;s blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://mikeenglish.net/blog/blog/categories/quotes/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://mikeenglish.net/blog/"/>
  <updated>2013-02-15T13:00:40-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://mikeenglish.net/blog/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Mike English]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Increasing Efficiency by Itself Doesn&#8217;t Employ People]]></title>
    <link href="http://mikeenglish.net/blog/2011/08/31/increasing-efficiency-by-itself-doesnt-employ-people/"/>
    <updated>2011-08-31T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://mikeenglish.net/blog/2011/08/31/increasing-efficiency-by-itself-doesnt-employ-people</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1></h1>

<p><a href="http://edge.org/conversation/the-local-global-flip" title="The Local-Global Flip, or, &quot;The Lanier Effect&quot;">Jaron Lanier</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p> There is this huge increase in efficiency, but the interesting thing is that increasing efficiency by itself doesn’t employ people. There is a difference between saving and making money when you’re unemployed. Once you’re already rich, saving money and making money is the same thing, but for people who are on the bottom or even in the middle classes, saving money doesn’t help you if you don’t have the money to save in the first place.</p></blockquote>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Microstructure Influences Macrostructure]]></title>
    <link href="http://mikeenglish.net/blog/2010/12/21/microstructure-influences-macrostructure/"/>
    <updated>2010-12-21T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://mikeenglish.net/blog/2010/12/21/microstructure-influences-macrostructure</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1></h1>

<p><a href="http://www.theatlantic.com/technology/archive/2010/12/the-hazards-of-nerd-supremacy-the-case-of-wikileaks/68217/" title="The Hazards of Nerd Supremacy: The Case of WikiLeaks">Jaron Lanier</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p>It is often the case that microstructure influences macrostructure. In the case of digital systems, where the microstructure is bits that are either completely on or completely off, it is easiest to build big things that tend to peg completely one way or another. You can easily be completely anonymous online, or utterly revealed, but it is hard to find an in-between spot.</p></blockquote>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Part of the Nature of Human Communication]]></title>
    <link href="http://mikeenglish.net/blog/2010/11/29/part-of-the-nature-of-human-communication/"/>
    <updated>2010-11-29T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://mikeenglish.net/blog/2010/11/29/part-of-the-nature-of-human-communication</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1></h1>

<p><a href="http://www.economist.com/blogs/democracyinamerica/2010/11/wikileaks">M.S. at The Economist’s Democracy in America Blog</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p>It’s part of the nature of human communication that one doesn’t always say the same thing to every audience. There are perfectly good reasons why you don’t always tell the same story to your boss as you do to your spouse. There are things Washington needs to tell Riyadh to explain what it’s just told Jerusalem and things Washington needs to tell Jerusalem to explain what it’s just told Riyadh, and these cables shouldn’t be crossed. There’s nothing wrong with this. It’s inevitable. And it wouldn’t make the world a better place if Washington were unable to say anything to Jerusalem without its being heard by Riyadh, any more than it would if you were unable to tell your spouse anything without its being heard by your boss.</p>

<p>…</p>

<p>[I]t definitely seems like we’re learning a lesson here: while information may want to be free, human beings are usually better off when it’s on a leash.</p></blockquote>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Facebook is Amazing]]></title>
    <link href="http://mikeenglish.net/blog/2010/11/21/facebook-is-amazing/"/>
    <updated>2010-11-21T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://mikeenglish.net/blog/2010/11/21/facebook-is-amazing</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1></h1>

<p><a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2010/11/21/technology/21brain.html?_r=1&amp;pagewanted=all" title="NYTimes: Growing Up Digital, Wired for Distraction">Woodside High School student, Sam Crocker</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p>Facebook is amazing because it feels like you’re doing something and you’re not doing anything. It’s the absence of doing something, but you feel gratified anyway.</p></blockquote>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Online Conversation Space]]></title>
    <link href="http://mikeenglish.net/blog/2010/11/18/the-online-conversation-space/"/>
    <updated>2010-11-18T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://mikeenglish.net/blog/2010/11/18/the-online-conversation-space</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1></h1>

<p><a href="http://technosociology.org/?p=212" title="Negotiating Privacy, Boundaries and Visibility in a Networked World: Why We Need to Move Beyond Opt-in vs. Opt-Out">Zeynep Tufekci</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p>While most people are aware that online places have different characteristics compared with offline spaces, it is hard to carry out everyday interactions under the shadow of this knowledge. For example, most college students interact online mostly with people they also interact with offline.  So, the online conversation space socio-mentally feels like hanging out with friends which tends to happen in enclosed spaces bounded by walls, entered through doors, scannable visibly, etc. It is hard to have a conversation with one’s close friends while constantly thinking: “Maybe this will end up in the news tommorow; maybe my boss will see this; maybe my professor will see this.” After awhile the online place becomes normalized into the intuitions we have from offline places because of the nature of the interaction in them.</p></blockquote>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
